{"tossups": [{"question": "While serving as Secretary of Foreign Affairs, this man was hit in the head with a rock during a riot which was directed at graverobbing doctors. This former president of the American Bible Society wrote the majority opinion in<em> Chisholm v. Georgia</em>. This man did not attend the Constitutional Convention but did write four of the first five Federalist Papers. This man\u2019s failure to end impressment was criticized after he negotiated a 1795 treaty with Great Britain. For the point, name this second governor of New York and first Chief Justice of the United States.", "answer": "John<b> Jay</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During the Caste War, many Maya fled from the Yucatan Peninsula to this country\u2019s town of Orange Walk. For the point, name this Central American country, formerly known as British Honduras.", "answer": "<b> Belize</b> (accept<b> British Honduras</b> until \u201cwhat is now this country\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this war, a general\u2019s claim that he could capture three state capitals in a span of two weeks led to Operation OAU. The Asaba Massacre occurred during this war, which inspired a Red Cross physician named Bernard Kouchner to found Doctors Without Borders. The Aburi Accord, which was signed in Ghana as Colonel Ojukwu\u2019s safety could not be guaranteed in his home country\u2019s northern region, broke down in 1967, leading to this war. For the point, name this civil war over a breakaway state in West Africa.", "answer": "<b> Nigerian Civil</b> War (accept Nigerian-<b>Biafra</b>n War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A mayor with this surname refused to disband the Municipal Police during the New York City Police Riot. Another man with this surname was accused of \u201cwanton slaughter\u201d by Secretary of War William Howard Taft after the First Battle of Bud Dajo. A mayor of New York with this surname advocated for the city to secede from the U.S. during the Civil War. The Moro Crater Massacre on Mindanao was carried out by a leader with this surname who worked with Teddy Roosevelt to found the Rough Riders. For the point, name this shared surname of Fernando and Leonard.", "answer": "<b> Wood</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "While on an expedition, this man produced a report on the possibility of a Russian invasion of Xinjiang [SHIN-JONG]. This man often signed his name as Kustaa while serving as regent for Frederick Charles of Hesse. Thor Damen recorded a conversation between Hitler and this man on his 75th birthday. This man led the White Guards during a 1919 Civil War and planned the construction of a defensive fortification on the Karelian Isthmus that was not complete by the Winter War. For the point, name this commander-in-chief of Finnish forces during World War Two.", "answer": "Carl Gustaf Emil<b> Mannerheim</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "George and Ira Gershwin parodied this man with the character Alexander Throttlebottom in their musical<em> Of Thee I Sing</em>. Joseph R. Burton\u2019s 1906 indictment on mail fraud charges led to this man\u2019s first appointment to the Senate for Kansas during which he spent eight days as President pro Tempore. This man\u2019s comment \u201cgood times are just around the corner\u201d was misattributed to his superior, contributing to an election loss in 1932. For the point, name this highest elected official of Native American descent, vice president under Herbert Hoover.", "answer": "Charles<b> Curtis</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this work, a Pokanoket guide named Hobomok is described as a \u201cfriend of the white men.\u201d The title character of this work served during the Eighty Years\u2019 War and was living in Leiden when he was hired as a military advisor and elected as commander by a group of English Separatists. The line \u201cWhy don\u2019t you speak for yourself, John?\u201d exposes the love triangle of this poem which the poem\u2019s author claimed was historical. The marriage of Priscilla Mullins and John Alden is featured in, for the point, what Henry Wadsworth Longfellow narrative poem set in Plymouth Colony?", "answer": "<em> The<b> Courtship of Miles Standish</b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Poetry"}, {}, {"question": "This man entrusted Percy Girouard with building a military railroad during a campaign in which this man defeated Osman Digna at the Battle of Atbara. Emily Hobhouse criticized this man\u2019s expansion of the internment camp system that he inherited from Lord Roberts. Killed when the HMS<em> Hampshire</em> hit a German mine in the North Sea, this man had earlier struck a decisive blow to the Mahdist revolt after a victory at Omdurman in Sudan. For the point, name this Secretary of State for War who organized Britain\u2019s volunteer army in the early days of World War One.", "answer": "Herbert<b> Kitchener</b> (accept 1st Earl<b> Kitchener</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Joseph Warren Revere raised the American flag for this nation after reading out naval commander John Sloat\u2019s proclamation. The Battle of Olompali was fought to preserve this nation\u2019s independence. This nation was founded by William B. Ide after the capture of Sonoma by Ezekiel Merritt. Mariano Guadalupe Vallejo was opposed by the founders of this nation, who were secretly supported by John C. Fr\u00b4emont. For the point, name this short-lived Republic declared during the Mexican-American War.", "answer": "<b> Bear Flag</b> Republic (accept<b> California</b> Republic)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The first recipient of this organization\u2019s Vare Trophy was Patty Berg, who was also its first president. This organization\u2019s first Major Championship was held in 1950 and was won a record four times by Mickey Wright and Betsy Rawls. Previously dominated by Americans, from 2015 to 2019, participants from South Korea and Thailand won 13 of the 15 major awards given by this organization. In 1996, Muffin Spencer-Devlin became the first out-lesbian competitor in this organization. For the point, name this oldest continuously operating US women\u2019s pro sports organization.", "answer": "<b> L</b>adies<b> P</b>rofessional<b> G</b>olf<b> A</b>ssociation Page 3", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "For the point, name this Indian empire ruled by Shivaji.", "answer": "<b> Maratha</b> Empire (accept<b> Maratha</b> Confederacy)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man led a failed siege of Lilybaeum after being crowned king of Sicily by the city of Syracuse. This leader was briefly King of Macedon, but lost support after allowing the pillage of the Macedonian royal tombs by the Gauls. This king died while fighting in the city of Argos after failing to win a siege of Sparta. This man defeated the Romans at Heraclea and Asculum with the help of his war elephants, but was unable to prevent the capture of Tarentum. For the point, name this king of Epirus who lends his name to a victory at great cost.", "answer": "<b> Pyrrhus</b> of Epirus", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man called for a 24-person elected group to provide education and job training and make moral inspections in<em> A Plan for Improving the Condition of the Free Blacks</em>. In another work, this man claimed that Native Americans were less savage than European settlers after a massacre conducted by the Paxton Boys. This man claimed in his autobiography, published three years after his 1790 death, that a desire to work for \u201cthe good of the people\u201d led him to invent a baffled stove. For the point, name this man, the first U.S. Postmaster General.", "answer": "Benjamin<b> Franklin</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This woman is named \u201cThe Accused\u201d in an Agnes De Mille ballet that also features the \u201cPastor\u201dand the \u201cMother.\u201d Five days before this woman\u2019s trial, Bertha Manchester was murdered, and this woman was a suspect. This woman said that she went away from her house for \u201c20 minutes or possibly a half an hour\u201d in her testimony for the murder of Abby Durfee Gray. After returning from New Bedford, this woman allegedly killed her father Andrew with \u201cforty whacks.\u201d For the point, name this woman who was acquitted in 1892 for axe murders in Fall River, Massachusetts.", "answer": "Lizzie<b> Borden</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man planned to train female doctors called<em> hakimas</em> by hiring French physician Antoine Clot [CLOH]. This man\u2019s son, Ibrahim, lost the Battle of Navarino in Greece, and his grandson, Isma\u2019il, defaulted on loans, leading to the seizure of the Suez Canal by the UK. This man, who murdered the Mamluks in the Cairo Citadel to consolidate power, founded a dynasty that was ended by Gamal Abdel Nasser. For the point, name this early 19th century ruler who modernized Egypt and broke it away from Ottoman rule.", "answer": "<b> Muhammad Ali</b> Pasha al-Mas\u2019ud ibn Agha of Egypt and the Sudan Page 4", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "The \u201cVoice of [these people],\u201d \u201cShorty\u201d Powers, coined the term \u201cA-OK.\u201d In 1985, Jake Garn became one of these people while serving as a US Senator from Utah. The Rogers Committee, which included Richard Feynman, investigated the death of seven members of this profession. Seven other members of this profession are profiled in Tom Wolfe\u2019s book<em> The Right Stuff</em>. Members of this profession were said to have \u201ctouched the face of God\u201d following the<em> Challenger</em> Disaster. For the point, name this profession of The Mercury Seven.", "answer": "<b> Astronaut</b>s (accept<b> Mercury</b> Seven prior to \u201cGarn\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The name of this policy was coined by sociologist Charles Moskos, who was presenting it to opponent Sam Nunn. A 2010 case based on a lawsuit from the Log Cabin Republicans challenged this policy and led to an injunction against a Cabinet department. When defending this policy in 2000, Moskos focused on the concept of \u201cmodesty rights\u201d involving showering, as opposed to the oft-cited \u201cunit cohesion\u201dargument. For the point, name this policy, created during the Clinton presidency and repealed in 2011, that allowed only closeted homosexuals to serve in the military.", "answer": "<b> Don\u2019t Ask, Don\u2019t Tell</b> (accept<b> DADT</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man attempted to restructure his country\u2019s economy with the help of Pedro Vuskovic. Another prominent advisor of this man, Carlos Prats, was removed after the failed Tank Putsch. To protect their holdings in the El Teniente mine, the Anaconda and Kennecott companies may have helped fund a coup against this man, who killed himself after rebels stormed the Palacio de La Moneda. This man nationalized the copper industry of his nation, prompting the CIA to back his overthrow. For the point, Augusto Pinochet succeeded what Marxist president of Chile?", "answer": "Salvador<b> Allende</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Ralph Perk, the mayor of this city, accidentally set his hair on fire while using a welding torch at a ribbon-cutting ceremony. Comedian Rich Little was threatened with a federal lawsuit by Representative Mary Rose Oakar after joking about this city that you could trick the Russians into not invading Poland by convincing them that it is this city. This city\u2019s branch of the United Way caused millions in damages in \u201cBalloonfest \u201886.\u201d The Clean Water Act was passed in the aftermath of a river in this city catching on fire. For the point, name this Ohio city at the mouth of the Cuyahoga River.", "answer": "<b> Cleveland</b>, Ohio", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This person became the subject of a widely-believed hoax after an interview on Russian television in which it was claimed that this person became a mushroom. Fanny Kaplan attempted to kill this leader outside of an arms factory. This man criticized his brother\u2019s interest in studying annelids, claiming he would never be a \u201crevolutionist.\u201d This leader responded to the Scissors Crisis by instituting a \u201cfree market subject to state control\u201d in the form of the New Economic Policy. For the point, name this first Chairman of the Council of People\u2019s Commisars.", "answer": "Vladimir<b> Lenin</b> (accept Vladimir Ilyich<b> Ulyanov</b>) Page 6", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A thinker from this country argued that overcoming nihilism requires the use of nihilism. Another thinker from this country developed the idea of pure consciousness in<em> An Inquiry Into the Good</em> and argued that the idea of nothingness is the foundation of this country\u2019s philosophy. In a tract on Zazen meditation, a thinker from this country attacked the Rinzai school for using koans rather than mindfulness. For the point, name this home country of Dogen, Keiji Nishitani, and Kitaro Nishida, whose modern philosophical activity centers on the Kyoto School.", "answer": "<b> Japan</b> (accept<b> Nippon</b>-koku; accept<b> Nihon</b>-koku)", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "A U.S. Ambassador to this country named John Gordon Mein was shot by rebels of this country\u2019s Rebel Armed Forces. A dictator from this country used a scorched earth campaign to annihilate nearly 600 villages in his \u201cbeans and guns\u201d plan and was overthrown by \u00b4Oscar Humberto Mej\u00b4\u0131a V\u00b4\u0131ctores in 1983. Efra\u00b4\u0131n R\u00b4\u0131os Montt led this country, which was home to a woman who protested this nation\u2019s 36-year civil war and atrocities against its indigenous Mayan people. For the point, name this Central American country, home to Nobel Peace Prize winner Rigoberta Mench\u00b4u.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Guatemala</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "American composer Conlon Nancarrow was held at the Gurs internment camp after fighting with this group. This unit adopted the song \u201cJarama Valley,\u201d named for its first significant battle. George Nathan was appointed brigade Chief of Staff of this unit before his death at the Battle of Brunete. This unit suffered many casualties during the Battle of the Ebro. For the point, name this volunteer unit of American soldiers who fought in the Spanish Civil War, named for a U.S. President.", "answer": "Abraham<b> Lincoln Brigade</b> (accept<b> XV International Brigade</b>, accept<b> XV Brigada Internacional</b>, accept Abraham<b> Lincoln Battalion</b>, accept<b> Brigada</b> Abraham<b> Lincoln</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Baroness Frederika Charlotte Riedesel kept a journal about her participation in this 19-day campaign. Troops captured after this campaign made up the Convention Army. Daniel Morgan legendarily ordered sniper Timothy Murphy to kill Simon Fraser at this campaign\u2019s Battle of Bemis Heights. John Burgoyne surrendered to Horatio Gates after this campaign. For the point, name this 1777 campaign, considered by many to be the turning point of the American Revolution.", "answer": "Battle(s) of<b> Saratoga</b> (accept<b> Saratoga</b> campaign) Page 7", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A leader of this unrecognized state signed the Internal Settlement with moderates Abel Muzorewa and Ndabaningi Sithole [SITH-ohl]. Following the use of Soviet-supplied missiles to shoot down two Viscount airliners, this country launched Operation Gatling, an incursion into Zambia. After a Unilateral Declaration of Independence supported by Ian Smith\u2019s \u201cFront\u201d named for this country, ZAPU and ZANU fought against it in a namesake Bush War. For the point, name this former African state that existed from 1965 to 1979 when it was renamed Zimbabwe.", "answer": "Republic of<b> Rhodesia</b> Page 8", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}